Finding aid to the Helen Sinclair Pittman Papers CA.MS.00346
Smith College Archives
Helen Sinclair Pittman Papers
1917-1979
Smith College Archives
Pittman, Helen Sinclair, 1899-1991
CA.MS.00346
0.833 linear feet (2 containers)
Physician and chairman of the Counselor Committee for the Smith College Health Service and Infirmary. Contains correspondence, pamphlets, publications, clippings, budget reports, and photograph album.
Biographical / Historical
Mary Helen Sinclair Pittman was born in 1899 in Halifax, Nova Scotia to Henry H. and Mary Agnes Sinclair Tremaine Pittman. Prior to Smith, she attended St. Agnes School in Albany, New York. Pittman graduated from Smith College in 1921 and received her M.D. from Johns Hopkins Medical School in 1927. Concerned primarily with the care of patients, Pittman became a noted physician in the medical field. Joining the staff of Massachusetts General Hospital in 1931, Pittman became the Director of the Pulmonary Clinic in 1942, and held that position for 17 years, until 1959. Her work with the 1942 Coconut Grove Club fire victims brought a better understanding to the medical world regarding the treatment of pulmonary damage secondary to the burns and the inhalation of toxic fumes. Not only was Pittman the first woman to be made president of the Suffolk District branch of the Massachusetts Medical Society, she was also a member of the Council of the Massachusetts Medical Society from 1936-1964, serving on both the Censors Committee and the Grievances Committee. Joining the staff of Harvard Medical School in 1946, Pittman ended her tenure at Harvard as a Clinical Associate in Medicine in 1959, and was an active member of the medical school's admissions committee. Pittman eventually rejoined the Smith community, becoming chairman of the Counselor Committee for the Health Service and Infirmary. Upon her retirement from Smith in 1966, Pittman received an honorary doctorate from the college for her service to the Smith community and her contributions to the development of modern medicine. She died in 1991 in Ayer, Massachusetts.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains correspondence, pamphlets, publications (including her 1934 article titled "The Pulmonary Complications: A Clinical Description"), clippings, budget reports, materials relating to her various organizational involvement (including the Smith College Infirmary and counseling services), and a photograph album from her days as a college student.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Helen Sinclair Pittman papers were donated to the Smith College Archives from a number of sources.
Pittman, Helen Sinclair, 1899-1991
- Biography
  - Biographical information, 1930-1977 (Box 975, Folder 1)
  - Awards and honors: consideration for Smith College Medal, 1966 (Box 975, Folder 2)
  - Awards and honors: honorary degree material, 1965-1966 (Box 975, Folder 3)
  - Commencement speech: St. Agnes School, 1967-1969 (Box 975, Folder 4)
  - Photograph album, 1917- 1920s (Box 975, Folder 5)
- Correspondence
  - Admission of women to Harvard Medical School, 1942-1943 (Box 975, Folder 6)
  - Harvard Medical School Admissions Committee, 1967-1972 (Box 975, Folder 7)
  - Interview for Dartmouth Magazine, 1979; undated (Box 975, Folder 8)
  - "Leaders in American Medicine", 1974-1975; undated (Box 975, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1928-1977; undated (Box 975, Folder 10)
  - Re: Joan Critchlow letter, 1971-1972; undated (Box 975, Folder 11)
  - Suffolk District Polio Program, 1962-1964 (Box 975, Folder 12)
- Committees (Box 976)
  - American College of Physicians, 1967-1968 (Box 976, Folder 1)
  - Board of Counselors: Health and Infirmary Committee, 1955-1959 (Box 976, Folder 2)
  - Board of Counselors: Health and Infirmary Committee, 1958-1960 (Box 976, Folder 3)
  - Board of Counselors: Health and Infirmary Committee, 1959-1960 (Box 976, Folder 4)
  - Board of Counselors: Health and Infirmary Committee, 1960-1961 (Box 976, Folder 5)
  - Board of Counselors: Health and Infirmary Committee, 1961-1962 (Box 976, Folder 6)
  - Board of Counselors: Health and Infirmary Committee, 1964-1965 (Box 976, Folder 7)
  - Board of Counselors: Health and Infirmary Committee, 1965-1966 (Box 976, Folder 8)
  - Massachusetts Medical Censors, 1956-1964 (Box 976, Folder 9)
  - Massachusetts Medical Headquarters, 1960-1965 (Box 976, Folder 10)
  - Massachusetts Medical Society, 1932-1965 (Box 976, Folder 11)
  - Suffolk District Medical Society, 1955-1964 (Box 976, Folder 12)
  - Suffolk District Medical Society, 1961-1965 (Box 976, Folder 13)
  - United Community Services, 1961-1965 (Box 976, Folder 14)
  - Publications, 1934-1969 (Box 976, Folder 15)